now let's discuss the relationship
between the dependencies we have seen
and what we call hazards in a pipeline a
dependence is the property of the
program alone we can just check whether
two instructions have a dependence
between them without any regard to what
the pipeline looks like in a particular
pipeline some dependencies will cause
problems potentially and some
dependencies cannot cause problems no
matter what let's look at an example of
this let's say we have the classical
five stage Pipeline with fetch decode
ALU memory and WR stages and let's
consider two instructions like this that
have an output dependence in this
particular pipeline I will show you that
this output dependence is never a
problem the ad will move through this
pipeline until the right stage and that
is when it will update R1 so let's look
at the cycle while the add is here and
the multiply is following behind it at
this point the multiplication has been
fetched has been decoded and read R4 and
R5 it read the correct value because
these are not affected by the ad and now
it's just sitting in the M stage because
it's not a memory operation it has the
value that it will deposit in R1 when
the ad leaves the pipeline in the next
cycle the multiply will get here and
have its right of R1 so as you can see
these instructions always write to R1 in
the correct order so the fact that there
is this output dependence doesn't mean
that we have to worry about it in this
pipeline this dependence will be
naturally satisfied in this pipeline
because the rights by different
instructions are always occurring in
program order in this pipeline now let's
consider a write after read dependence
let's say that there is a subtract
instruction here that overrides
R4 that was read by the multiply at the
point where multiply reads R4 the
subtract is being fetched so the
multiply reads the value of R4 that was
not affected by the subtract later on
when the multiply is done the subtract
will finally write to
R4 and that again means that the fact
that there is a dependence between the
re
and the right in these consecutive
instructions is never a problem for our
pipeline because the read of R4 in the
multiply occurs many cycles before the
subtract overwrites that value so again
we have a dependence that cannot become
a problem in our pipeline now let's look
at what happens when there is a true
dependence in this pipeline in this case
R4 here should be used by the next
instruction The Divide is reading R4 in
a cycle where the subtract is here
clearly at that time subtract didn't put
its R4 value in the register R4 it is
actually just Computing that value so
when the Divide reads register R4 it's
reading a stale value of R4 that existed
before the subtract several Cycles later
when the subtract is writing to that
register the Divide has already computed
its value and the next cycle divide will
write that bogus value into the register
so pretty much the Divide read the wrong
value for four computed with that wrong
value and then eventually deposits that
wrong value into a register so clearly
this true dependence here is a problem
in our pipeline if we just let things go
and flow through the pipeline we will
have the wrong result deposited into r10
by the divide the situation when a
dependence can cause a problem in a
pipeline is called a hazard so a hazard
occurs when a dependence results in
incorrect execution of one or more
instructions hazards are a property of
both the program because you cannot have
a hazard unless you have a
dependence but also of the pipeline
itself how the dependence is interacting
with the pipeline so for example we have
seen that output and anti-de
dependencies in this particular pipeline
cannot become hazards but true
dependencies can now I will show you
that not all through dependencies are
hazards in this
pipeline in this case we have seen that
a dependence between consecutive
instructions creates a hazard in this
pipeline let's say that the right to R7
occurs in this multiplying inst
struction and that we now have an xor
that uses R1 and R7 let's now see
whether there is a dependence between
the ADD and xor yes there is R1 produced
by the ad should be used by the xor and
there is also a dependence between the
multiply and the xor but let's see if
these dependencies are hazards in this
particular pipeline when the exor is in
the decode stage The Divide is in the
ALU stage the subtract is in the M stage
and the multiply is in the right stage
and the add has left the pipeline it was
writing to R1 in the previous cycle so
as you can see the dependence between
the ad and the xor is not a hazard in
this pipeline pretty much in this
pipeline if there are three or more
instructions between the producing and
the consuming
instruction then the consuming
instruction reads the register after the
producing one has already written it
however the dependence on R7 between the
multiply and X or is potentially a
problem in this pipeline because the
exor is reading
R7 in the cycle during which multiply is
writing it to the register so if this
write completes near the end of the
clock cycle and this
read is happening near the beginning of
the clock cycle the exor will not read
the R7 produced by the multiply in this
pipeline we can tell that a true
dependence is not a hazard if there is
three or more instructions in between
the producing and the consuming
instruction but it is a hazard if there
is fewer than three instructions between
them in this case there are only two
instructions in between and that's why
we still have a hazard